A Guide to the Papers of Elizabeth Calvert Page Dabney 1812-1943
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Elizabeth Calvert Page Dabney 1812-1943
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
RG 17-3 B1
1 Hollinger box and 1 Document case
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Calvert Page Dabney, July 1978.
Biographical/Historical Information
Elizabeth Calvert Page Dabney is a former Professor of English at Old Dominion University and a descendant of an old Norfolk family. The history of Elizabeth Calvert Page Dabney's family includes the histories of the Dabneys, the Pages, the Gordons, the Whittles, and the Loyalls.
The Pages are an old and well-known Virginia family historically distinguished for their devotion to the Episcopal Church. They are related by marriage to the famous Revolutionary War General "Light Horse Harry" Lee and General Robert E. Lee. A known member of the Page family, Richard Lucien Page, served the United States Navy in the War of 1812 and in the Mexican War. When Virginia seceded from the Union in 1861, he resigned his commission to the Union and was commissioned in the Navy of the Confederacy. He was later captured as a prisoner of war, and released after the Civil War.
The Gordon family came to Virginia from Scotland in the 1700s. Samuel and Basil Gordon, and Samuel's nephew, were the first of their family in Virginia. The three men married three sisters who were the daughters of William Knox of Culpepper County, Virginia. They settled near Fredericksburg. In 1812, after the death of their father, the Gordons returned home to Scotland. Samuel and Agnes Knox Gordon remained in Scotland and England for the next twenty years before returning to Virginia.
The Loyalls lived in Norfolk during the Civil War. Camilla Frances Loyall kept a diary of her experiences during this time. Her accounts include the capture of Norfolk by the Union in 1862.
Scope and Content Information
The papers contained in this collection date from 1812 to 1943. They include family diaries, speeches and essays about the Confederacy during the Civil War, old newspapers and booklets, and various legal documents and certificates. Of particular note are Camilla Frances Loyall's first hand accounts of Norfolk during the Civil War, and its capture by General Wool and the Union in 1862.
Contents List
- The Gordon Family-Genalogical Data (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
- This diary recounts life in Scotland and England, then follows the journey to the United States and then life in Virginia (typed transcript). 1812-1839 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
- This diary, written in Norfolk, Virginia during the Civil War, describes the Union's occupation of Norflok and the city's reaction to one of its own, Admiral David Farragut, leading the U.S. Naval Forces in the capture of New Orleans. May 1-June 14, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
- Relates to a story of Whittle's first action in the United States Navy, when he was serving as a midshipman on the USS Preble. The action occured off Anton Lizardo near Vera Cruz, Mexico and involved U.S. Naval vessels and two steamships flying no flag whose objective was to assist General Miramon in his rebellion against President Juarez of Mexico. The two vessels sailed from Havana, Cuba. March 1860 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
- written by Captain C. Whittle, an officer on board. 1910 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
- Handwritten text of a speech delivered to the United Daughters of the Confedracy, Shaw-Niemyer (?) Camp, Berkley, Virginia. (no date) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
- Jefferson Davis Home Association Life Membership-William C. Whittle (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
- Certificate of Merit-Edmonia L. Whittle-First Fighter Command Auxiliary Aircraft Warning Service, January 1, 1943 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
- Confederate Bond-$500 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
- Proceedings of the Twenty-Ninth Annual Meeting of the Grand Camp, Confederate Veterans, Proceedings, Department of Virginia, October 24-26, 1916 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
- Address by Miss Mildred Lewis Rutherford, Historian General, United Daughters of the Confedracy-"Historical Sins of Omission and Commission "-San Francisco, California, October 22, 1915 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
- Between Samuel Hirsch and Sarah Alexina Page in regard to the sale of a lot and dwelling at 161 Duke Street, Norfolk, November 10, 1898 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
- Receipt for payment of real estate commission by Richard L. Page to Pannill Bros., November 10, 1898 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
- Receipt of the purchase of a slave, Catherine, with her two children, by Mr. R.L. Page, December 27, 1854 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
- by the Reverend Carl E. Grammer in Christ Church, Norfolk, August 18, 1901 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
- Report of the Ivanhoe Land and Improvement Company of Ivanhoe, Wythe County, Virginia, 1890-1892 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
- Booklet on Norfolk History, 1904 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
- The Gray Jacket, November 1893 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
- The Gray Jacket, December 1893 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
- The Gray Jacket, March 1894 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
- The Gray Jacket, November 1897 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
- The Jamestown Bulletin-Jamestown Exposition, July 1906 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
- Charleston News and Courier-"Reunion-United Confederate Veterans," May 10, 1899 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
- Raleigh News and Observer, May 11, 1902 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
- Norfolk Landmark, June 11, 1905 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 25)
- Norfolk Virginian-Pilot, February 10, 1918 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 26)
- The History and Adventure of Little James and Mary by Lucy Watkins, 1819 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 27)
- Envelope postmarked and addressed to Captain William C. Whittle, July 11, 1885 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 28)
- Graduation Certificates (Box-folder Box 1, Folders 1-3)